Guide to the Stanford University Map Collection SC1049
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University map collection
1853-1997
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University
SC1049
422 item(s) and 3 volumes
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Scope and Content
The maps in this collection pertain to the University campus, to other lands owned by Jane and Leland Stanford or the University, and to adjacent communities.
Stanford University -- Architecture.; Stanford University -- Buildings.; Stanford University -- Facilities.; Stanford University -- History.; Maps; Campus planning -- California -- Stanford; Stanford University; Stanford University
- Maps
  - Before Stanford, Series 1; 13 item(s)
    Scope and Contents note
    These are maps of the campus area as it was before or when Leland and Jane Stanford purchased it. A few maps of adjacent communities are also included.
    - Palo Alto in the late 1840s from later surveys and other sources. Includes "Notes to Accompany the Map" by Alan K. Brown., 1963; M001 (Box A1)
    - Map of Mayfield Grange the property of George Gordon, surveyed by Alfred Poett, circa 1869; M002 (Box B1)
    - Map of the region adjacent to the Bay of San Francisco. State Geological Survey of California. Julius Bien, lith., 1873; M003 (Box Na1)
    - Ayrshire Farm, levels, circa 1880; M004 (Box D2)
    - D. Hoag property south of Searsville Road, Santa Clara County, Plat of a survey. Herrmann Brothers, 1876; M005 (Box Na1)
    - Searsville damsite. Surveyed and drawn by H.E. Dikeman, 1888; M006 os
    - Map of lands situated in Santa Clara and San Mateo Counties, the Property of Leland Stanford, Surveyed at Request of Ariel Lathrop. John Coombe., 1883; M007 os
    - Map of lands situated in Santa Clara and San Mateo Counties, Property of Leland Stanford, surveyed at the request of Ariel Lathrop. John Coombe., 1883-1885; M008 os
    - No title. [Property of Leland Stanford in San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties.] Unsigned., after 1885; [1883? - 1887?]; M009 os
    - Plat of the Rancho El Corte de Madera finally confirmed to Mazimo Martinez. Surveyed under the orders of the U.S. Surveyor General by T.S. Stephens, Dep. Sur., July 1857; M010 (Box D2)
    - Villa land along the San Jose Railroad between Redwood City and Mountain View / Published by A. Rosenfield; Lith Britten C., circa 1868/69; M011 (Box D2)
    - Map of the original Menlo Park Tract... to be sold at auction on Tuesday, May 4th, 1869 by Maurice Dore Co. / Britten Rey, lithographers, M012 (Box Na1)
    - Map of the survey for a partition of the San Francisquito Rancho. Ordered by the Probate Court Feb. 28, 1853, surveyed May 1853, M013 (Box D2)
    - Plat of the Rancho Rincon de San Francisquito finally confirmed to Teodoro and Secundino Robles.... [copy], 1863; M0014
  - Stock Farm and Other Lands, Series 2; 29 item(s)
    These maps are of the Palo Alto Stock Farm, the land in Santa Clara County that Leland and Jane Stanford purchased as a country home and trotting horse farm which later became the campus of Stanford University, and other land owned by the Stanfords throughout California, both before and after the establishment of the University.
    - Property of Leland Stanford filed in County Assessors office, April 18, 1884; M100 (Box D2)
    - Santa Rita Rancho file, undated; M101 (Box D2)
    - Stanford Heights [San Francisco?], undated; M102 (Box A1)
    - Stanford Heights, San Francisco [real estate brochure], M102b
    - Stanford Heights, San Francisco [real estate brochure], undated; M102b (Box D2)
    - Seale Rancho File. San Jose Abstract and Title Company. [shows land bought by L. Stanford 1876-78 for Palo Alto Stock Farm], undated; M103 (Box C1)
    - Attorneys map of Las Pulgas Rancho, [one color showing lands purchased under Pulgas Patent on the Dennis Martin tract by Leland Stanford.], undated; M104 (Box B1)
    - Map of the subdivision of a portion of the San Miguel Rancho, city and county of San Francisco, property of Hon. Leland Stanford. Suveyed by Shackelford and Barker., 1890; M105 (Box Na1)
    - Map of the Calistoga or Little Geysers and the Hot Sulphur Springs, Napa County California. Surveyed by T.W. Morgan. Lith. by Britton and Rey, S.F., Jan., 1871; M106 (Box Na1)
    - Map of the Government (Gwin) Ranch, Contra Costa County, as subdivided for J. Rosenthal and G. Bates. J.A. McMahon., 1884; M107 os
    - Map of the Gwin Ranch, commonly known as Government Ranch, belonging to the estate of Leland Stanford, Contra Costa County., circa 1880; M108 os
    - Topographical map of the western portion of Stanford Vina Ranch in Butte and Tehama Counties. J. Thompson., 1916-1918; M109 os
    - Map of the Stanford-Durham Ranch, being the southerly part of Rancho Esquon in Butte County, California. M.C. Polk., circa 1880's; M110 os
    - Sale of Lots Map of the Stanford-Durham Ranch, being the southerly part of Rancho Esquon in Butte County, California. Property division for sale in lots provided. M.C. Polk., circa 1880's; M110a os
    - Untitled map showing lands of Stanford Estate, Leland Stanford Junior University Trust, Mayfield lots, Palo Alto Stock Farm, and private lots along San Francisquito Creek., circa 1880's; M111 os
    - Official map of Tehama County / Board of Supervisors, Tehama. Surveyed by W.F. Luning., 1903; M112 (Box A3)
    - Estate of Leland Stanford, deceased. Unusual offering of ranch property by order of Mrs. Jane L. Stanford, executrix. Property for sale by McAfee Brothers, S.F., circa 1897; M113 (Box B1)
    - Estate of Leland Stanford, deceased. Unusual offering of ranch property by order of Mrs. Jane L. Stanford, executrix. Property for sale by McAfee Brothers, S.F., circa 1897; M113_1 (Box A1)
    - Topology and Geology of the Stanford - Durham Ranch / A Property of the LSJU in Butte County, California. Done under the direction of J. C. Branner by E. C. Templeton, M114
    - Palo Alto residence and stock farm of Leland Stanford. Santa Clara County, California. Surveyed, laid out and superintended by Alfred Poett., 1880; M150 (Box C1)
    - Palo Alto Stock Farm, established 1876, discontinued, 1903., undated; M151 (Box C1)
    - [Palo Alto Stock Farm - trotting tracks, paddocks and barns] No title, date, or other identifying information., undated; M152 (Box C1)
    - Sketch of Ranch shewing [sic] farm operations 1878 to 1879, Fremont Township, Santa Clara County. Filed in Co. Assessors Office, March 6, 1882., M153 (Box C1)
    - Palo Alto Stock Farm, 1876-1903, after survey at request of Stanford. [3 sheets of maps; 6 pages of notes], 1883-1892; M154 (Box C1)
    - Palo Alto residence and stock farm of Leland Stanford. Santa Clara County, California. Surveyed, laid out and superintended by Alfred Poett., 1880; M155 os
    - Profile showing bottom of San Francisquito Creek 5000 ft. up stream from San Jose and S.F. County Road Bridge., undated; M156 (Box Na1)
    - Plot of New Mayfield Road, undated; M157 (Box Na1)
    - Residence and grounds of Leland Stanford at Palo Alto, undated; M158 (Box Na1)
    - Residence and grounds of Leland Stanford at Palo Alto, undated; M158 (copy) (Box A1)
    - Map of the "Brick Kiln Field" otherwise known as the southern portion of Lot 25. Leased for 1 year... to Steve Anderson. Date of lease Oct. 1, 1896., M159 (Box C1)
    - Hogan tract, 1898; M160 (Box Na3)
    - Hogan tract, M160B (Box Na1)
  - Proposed Campus up to 1900, Series 3; 51 item(s)
    These maps include plans by F. L. Olmsted & Company, topographical maps, road profiles and plans, and some utility plans.
    - Stanford University Maps - Map of the Leland Stanford Junior University and surroundings at Palo Alto, California. H.B. Shackelford, chief engineer., 1891; M200 (Box B1)
    - Stanford University Maps - Map of the Leland Stanford Junior University and surroundings at Palo Alto, California. H.B. Shackelford, chief engineer., 1891; M200 (Box C1)
    - Map of the Leland Stanford Junior University and surroundings at Palo Alto, California. H.B. Shackelford, chief engineer., 200C (Box D2)
    - Stanford University maps - no title, date or other identifying information., circa 1888; M201_1 (Box D2)
    - Stanford University maps - no title, date or other identifying information. (slightly revised version of 201.1), circa 1888; M201_2 (Box B1)
    - Topographical map of all lands situated in Santa Clara County belonging to Leland Stanford Junior University at Palo Alto, California. Surveyed at the request of F. L. Olmsted., circa 1888; M202 (Box B1)
    - Topographical map of all lands situated in Santa Clara County belonging to Leland Stanford Junior University. Surveyed at the request of F.L. Olmsted. J.G. Gould., 1886-1887; M203 os
    - Topographical map of all lands situated in Santa Clara County belonging to Leland Stanford Junior University. Surveyed at the request of F.L. Olmsted. J.G. Gould., 1886-1887; M203 copy (Box D2)
    - Topographical map of all lands situated in Santa Clara County belonging to Leland Stanford Junior University. Surveyed at the request of F.L. Olmsted. J.G. Gould., 1886-1887; M203 copy (Box C1)
    - [Stanford Universtiy, 1888] Revised plan as platted in 1888. Shows quadrangle and adjoining areas., M204 (Box Na1)
    - [Stanford Universtiy, 1888] Revised plan as platted in 1888. Shows quadrangle and adjoining areas., M204 neg (Box C1)
    - Topographical map of part of grounds, Leland Stanford Junior University., 1888; M205 os
    - Topographical map of grounds, Leland Stanford Junior University at Palo Alto... Surveyed at the request of F. Olmsted. J.G. McMillan., circa 1880's; M206 os
    - Map of the Leland Stanford Jr. University and surrounding area, Palo Alto. Proposed campus plan (includes Palo Alto Stock Farm bldgs.)., c.1880s; M207 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Topographical map of grounds. Surveyed at the request of F.L. Olmsted C.E., circa 1885?; M208 (Box Na1)
    - Profiles. Profile showing surface of ground from actual survey. F.L. and J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., circa 1885?; M209 os (Box A4)
    - [Dormitory No. 1, Professors' Homes Nos. 1, 2, 3], circa 1887?; M210 (Box Na1)
    - [Plan of Inner Quad Corner], circa 1887?; M211 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - [Northwest Corner of Main Quad Northeast Corner of West Lateral Quad], circa 1887?; M212 (Box Na1)
    - [North Entrance System to Quad], circa 1887?; M213 (Box D2)
    - Studies. [Overall plan of University], circa 1887?; M214 (Box D2)
    - [General Plan], circa 1887?; M215 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - [General Plan], circa 1887?; M216 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - [West Half of Oval and Related Streets], circa 1888?; M217 (Box Na1)
    - Parking North of Quadrangles, Feb. 14, 1889; M218 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - [Partial Three Quad Plan], circa 1889?; M219 os (Box Nf0)
    - [General Plan], March 28, 1889; M220 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Working Plan for NE Quarter. F.l. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., June 6, 1889; M221 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Working Plan for N.W. Quarter. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., June 6, 1889; M222 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Working Plan for S.E. Quarter. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., June 6, 1889; M223 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Working Plan for S.W. Quarter. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., June 6, 1889; M224 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Profile of H S Centre Line. Main Quadrangle Approaches., undated; M225 os
    - Profile of University Avenue "North and South Centre Line". F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., July 22, 1889; M226 os (Box A4)
    - Profile of Centre Line North South. (Olmsted?), undated; M227 os (Box A4)
    - Profile of Road North of Quadrangle, Profile of Road East of Quadrangle, Profile of Road South of Quadrangle, Profile of Road West of Quadrangle. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., June 28, 1887; M228 (Box C1)
    - Profile Showing Surface of Centre Line of Present Avenue #37. Figured by Mr. Olmsted., July 23, 1889; M229 os (Box A4)
    - Cross Section of University Avenue. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., July 22, 1889; M230 (Box Na1)
    - Revised Profiles for Sewerage of Main Quadrangle and Adjacent Roads with Extension to Flush Tank. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., Sept. 3, 1889; M231 (Box D2)
    - [Drainage Plan], undated; M232 os (Box Nf0)
    - [Main Quad Drainage Plan?], circa 1889?; M233 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Working Plan for Grading and Drainage of Main Quadrangle and Adjacent Roads. F.L. J.C. Olmsted, Landscape Architects., July 15, 1889; M234 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Plan and Profile for Tunnel from Main Quadrangle to Dormitory. F.L. Olmsted Co., Landscape Archtects., Sept. 5, 1889; M235 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Plan and Profile for Tunnel from Main Quadrangle to Dormitory. F.L. Olmsted Co., Landscape Architects. Shepley, Rutan, Coolidge, Architects, circa 1889?; M236 os
    - Olmsted plans and drawings, 6 plans [copies], circa 1887; M237 (Box C1)
    - Olmsted's Working Plans, sheets 1-4. 4 quarters., undated; M238 os (Folder Tin Room)
    - Leland Stanford Jr. University. Study of Outer Neighborhood Roads., Sept. 1889; M239 (Box Na1)
    - L.S.J.U. Plan Showing Electric Lighting Around Quadrangle, Dormitories and Art Museum., undated; M239_1 os
    - Topographical map of grounds Leland Stanford Jr. University at Palo Alto... Surveyed at the request of F. L. Olmsted. J. G. McMillan., circa 1880s; M241 (Box C1)
    - Topographical map of grounds Leland Stanford Jr. University at Palo Alto... Surveyed at the request of F. L. Olmsted. J. G. McMillan., M241a (Box C1)
    - Topographical map of grounds Leland Stanford Jr. University at Palo Alto... Surveyed at the request of F. L. Olmsted. J. G. McMillan., 1880; M241b
    - Plan for Sewerage for the University Buildings and Surrounding Residential District. Waring, Chapman and Farquhar, engineers, October 1889; M242 (Box B1)
    - Revised Plan for Sewerage of Main Quadrangle and Adjacent Roads with Extension to Flush Tank. Waring, Chapman and Farquhar, engineers., October 1889; M243 (Box B1)
    - Leland Stanford Jr. Univ. N.W. Qr. [quarter] showing rail road, pipe line and finished grades about Museum., circa 1889; M244 (Box B1)
  - Student Guide Maps, Series 4; 50 item(s)
    These are maps of the campus, often with the adjacent communities of Mayfield and Palo Alto, that were included in the Stanford University Register, Directory or other official publications.
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 1900, 1960-70s; M300 (Box A1)
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students, 1923-1944; M300 (Box B1)
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 1991-1993; M300 (Box C1)
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 1995-1997; M300 (Box D2)
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 1900-1970s; M300a
    - The Campus of Stanford University at Palo Alto, California. Interior of brochure: Welcome to Stanford University., 1950-1963; M300b
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 1912-1944; M300c
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students. 1991 Bookstore Edition, M300d (Box C1)
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students. 1991-1993, M300e
    - The Campus of Stanford University at Palo Alto, California., 1960; M300f
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 2005-2009; M300g
    - Maps of Stanford University and vicinity usually part of the Register, Directory, or other official publications for students., 1995-2004; M300h
  - Commercial Guide Maps, Series 5; 11 item(s)
    Included in this category are maps drawn by Della Taylor, Edward M. Farmer, and Arthur Lites.
    - Map showing Stanford University present and future. Drawn by Della Taylor. Published by Stanford University Press., 1928; M400 (Box Na1)
    - Map showing Stanford University present and future. Drawn by Della Taylor. Published by Stanford University Press. Sepia reproduction., 1928; M400a (Box A1)
    - Stanford University by Edward M. Farmer., 1934; M401 (Box C2)
    - Stanford University by Arthur Lites., 1943; M402 (Box D2)
    - Stanford University by Arthur Lites., 1943; M402b
    - Stanford University by Arthur Lites. B/W photostatic copy, 1943; M402a (Box Na1)
    - [Stanford University]. By Ralph Buchwalter., 1953; M403 (Box B1)
    - The Campus of Stanford University at Palo Alto, California by P.S. King., 1960's?; M404 (Box D2)
    - Stanford University campus by Della Taylor Hoss. Published by Stanford University Press., 1950; M405 (Box A1)
    - All about the farm. Illustrated map of Stanford University, tour of the campus with views of buildings and grounds. Compiled by James Ladd Delkin., 1940; M406 (Box C2)
    - Stanford University by Stanley Milne., 1930; M407 (Box B1)
    - Stanford. Published by Guide and Visitors Service Office of Public Affairs, M408
    - Stanford University. Published and sold by the Stanford Student Guide Service. Same version published by University Relations, M409
    - Stanford University. Published by Visitors Information Services, M410
  - Miscellaneous (mostly non-campus), Series 6; 38 item(s)
    Most of these maps pertain to communities adjacent to the campus, including Mayfield, Woodside, Palo Alto, and Menlo Park. Other subjects include San Francisquito Creek, Searsville Lake, Greystone Quarry, and plots owned by individuals.
    - Map of College Terrace, Mayfield, Santa Clara, County, California. A.H. Merkins., 1900?; M500 (Box D2)
    - A cartograph of Woodside, California. Limned by Marian Morris Goodman., 1954; M501 (Box C2)
    - Map of the roads and trails in reach of Stanford University prepared for the Stanford University outing club. A.M. Strong., 1899; M502
    - Chart locating and identifying trees planted around the Main Library, the Art Gallery, and the Hoover Library., undated; M503 (Box Na1)
    - Presbyterian church, Menlo Park, California. Plan shewing [sic] pews., 1890; M504 (Box D2)
    - Map of the Ormondale Ranch situated in San Mateo County, California. Punnett, Parez Hutchison, civil engineers., October, 1937; M505a (Box C2)
    - Map of the Ormondale Ranch situated in theSan Mateo County, California. Punnett, Parez Hutchison, civil engineers. Continuation of M505a., 1937; M505b (Box C2)
    - The Coon and Felt tracts, San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties, California. McAfee Brothers., 189-?; M506 (Box B1)
    - Trail map, Menlo Circus Club. Especially prepared by Rand McNally., 1953; M507 (Box C2)
    - Topography and culture on a portion of the San Francisquito Creek drainage area lying between the Searsvile Reservoir and Los Trancos Creek. James and Waters, civil engineers., June, 1941; M508 (Box Na1)
    - Radio propagation lab field site map. Tatum [?]., 1958; M509 (Box D2)
    - View of Palo Alto showing Stanford University and College Terrace. W.H. Bull, San Mateo., circa 1905; M510 (Box A1)
    - Contour Map of Woodside Country Club. F.S. Isaacs., 1927; M511 os
    - Woodside Country Club, Approximate Area to be Watered. American Golf Course Construction Company., 1930; M512 os
    - Map of the Property of Joseph M. MacDonough, Situated in San Mateo County. Punnett, Parey and Hutchison., 1925; M513 os
    - Map of Stanford University and Vicinity, showing portion of campus in academic use and street map of Palo Alto. Unsigned., 1934; M514 os
    - Regional Map of the City of Palo Alto, California, including academic portion of Stanford campus and radius points for drawing the 1 1/2 mile [liquor] limit. J.F. Byxbee., 1926; M515 os
    - Topographical map of Palo Alto, showing University grounds [in blue shade]. Curtis M. Barker., 1888; M516 os (Box Nf0)
    - Map Showing Lands Adjacent to Leland Stanford Junior University in Santa Clara and San Mateo Counties. Map includes names of lot owners, boundaries and acreages. Unsigned., circa 1880s; M517 os
    - Palo Alto and Vicinity, compiled from Latest Official Data. Map includes block and lot numbers and numbered key for university bldgs. Unsigned., 1905; M518 os
    - Palo Alto and Vicinity. Compiled from Official Records of San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties. Published by Palo Alto Chamber of Commerce. C.E. Hunt., circa 1965?; M519 (Box D2)
    - Map of the Southern Portion of the San Francisco Peninsula. Map includes elevations, creeks, towns, highways and railway lines. J.P. Mitchell., 1909; M520 (Box D2)
    - Map of Watervliet Township, New York [birthplace of Leland Stanford, Sr.]. Enlargement of Map #31, New Topographical Atlas of Albany and Schenectady Counties, 1866. Unsigned., circa 1866?; M521 (Box C2)
    - Thomas Bros. map of Palo Alto and vicinity including Redwood City, Atherton, Menlo Park, Los Altos, and Mountain View., circa 1930; M522
    - Map showing Palo Alto and vicinity. The University Realty Co., 1910; M523 (Box D2)
    - Palo Alto quadrangle, California: Topographic sheet. U.S. Geological Survey, R.B. Marshall, topographer., 1899; M525 (Box D2)
    - Searsville Lake., 1919; M526 os
    - San Francisquito Creek., 1918; M527 os
    - Birdseye view of Menlo Park and vicinity showing tracts of Stanford Park, Baywood Field, Ringwood Park, circa 1900; M528 (Box D2)
    - Plat of the property of E. Clogenson, undated; M529 (Box D2)
    - Palo Alto Quadrangle, California: Topographic sheet. U.S. Geological Survey, R.B. Marshall, topographer. Reprint of the 1899 edition., 1944; M530 (Box C2)
    - Map of Santa Clara County compiled for the Santa Clara Valley Land Loan and Insurance Agency, circa 1885; M531
    - Map of land at Menlo Park belonging to John T. Doyle, Eugene Casserly, Jos. A. Donohue, H.H. Haight others, undated; M532
    - Palo Alto Quadrangle, California: Topographic sheet. U.S. Geological Survey, R.B. Marshall, topographer., 1899; M533 (Box SAL)
    - Palo Alto Quadrangle, California. 15 minute series (topographic).U.S. Geological Survey., 1948; M534
    - [Santa Clara County]. Shows Stanford, Palo Alto, Mayfield, Mountain View and specific lots/tracts within. Bottom half missing., circa 1910; M535 (Box D2)
    - [Greystone] Quarry Area, Geology and Topography, L.S.J.U. Geological Survey. Surveyed by A. W. Ambrose, C. H. Beal and W. F. Dietrich., July 1912; M536 (Box B1)
    - Map showing proposed extension of Palo Alto Avenue across the Southern Pacific Railroad Company's Right of Way and Stanford Estate to the San Francisco and San Jose Road., M541
    - Map of San Francisco Gray Line Tour Routes. From San Francisco Hotel Greeters Guide August 1948., M542
    - Camp Fremont, Menlo Park, 20th National Guard Infantry Division Camp, Nov. 15, 1917 [photocopy of original in U. S. Army Archives, M543
    - Camp Fremont, Palo Alto, [photocopy of original in U. S. Army Archives] - map of SU/Palo Alto/Menlo Park showing location of Camp Fremont on either side of San Francisquito creek (SU and Menlo Park), M544
  - Campus Miscellany, Series 7; 68 item(s)
    Included among these maps are planting schemes, location of the Peninsular Railroad line on campus, plans for Junipero Serra Boulevard, and housing subdivisions.